Hi, welcome back to the Lam Rim.
We've reached now,
we had MAR SHES,
which is I recognize that
everyone has been my mom.
And then DRIN DRAN,
I think about all the good
things they did for me
when they were my mom,
even the ant crawling across
the floor of the bathroom.
DRIN GZO
We just had to pay her back
with more than she gave you.
Give her Buddhahood
in exchange for bringing you up.
Now we've reached the
fourth step which is called
YID 'ONG BYAMS PA
You guys all know the word BYAMS PA
It's like Maitri, my grandson's name.
But YID 'ONG means beautiful.
They look beautiful to you.
The people look beautiful to
you and you feel love for them.
So we're going to cover
now the fourth part.
BZHI PA YID 'ONG GI BYAMS PA BSGOM PA LA
That's the next line.
Let's read the next paragraph.
DE'I RNAM PA NI SEMS CAN RNAMS
SNYING DU SDUG CING GCES LA PHANGS PA'I
RNAM PAR 'CHAR BA ZHIG STE
You reach this fourth level
when you look at people
and you feel like they look
super beautiful to you.
Like you're just around normal people,
and you're just doing
normal things with them,
and then you just look
at them and you're like,
"Man, they're so beautiful."
Not necessarily physically, right?
But you feel this beauty
in the people around you.
It's kind of like when
you're working together
with a bunch of people.
You do some hard work together,
and you get the work done,
and then everyone looks beautiful to you.
RNAM PAR 'CHAR BA means
that's how it looks to you.
DGE BSHES PO TO BAS AA MA RGAN MO ZHIG LA
So DGE BSHES PO TO BAS was
one of those Kadampa lamas
about a thousand years ago in Tibet.
And one older woman,
AA MA RGAN MO
means older woman,
came up to him, and she said,
"What is this beautiful love?"
What does it mean to have that love
where you see the people
around you as really beautiful?
What is that?
How do you describe that?
How do you get that?
And he said,
KHYOD KYI BU THOD LE
KOR LA JI LTAR BYAMS PA
It's the kind of love that
you have for your son.
Her son's name was THOD LE KOR.
So it's like John, or Pachi, or something.
He says that the love you
have for your son, Pachi,
that's beautiful love.
And the goal is to have it for everybody.
You see him as super beautiful
because he is your son.
But now can you have that for everybody?
BYAMS PA NI KHYOD KYI BU THOD
LE KOR LA JI LTAR BYAMS PA
DE LTAR YIN GSUNGS PA
LTAR SEMS CAN THAMS CAD BU
YID DU 'ONG BA DANG 'DRA BAR
When you see all the people
around you as very beautiful,
they strike you as very beautiful.
MTHONG BA LA YID 'ONG GI BYAMS PA
That's what we call step number four
in developing bodhisattva's vision,
bohichitta, is called beautiful love.
Sees people as beautiful.
We have that picture of
the mom with her child.
You can imagine
that she sees her child very beautiful.
She has a crush on her baby.
She sees him as very, very beautiful.
All right, let's go back to the text.
'DI LA DMIGS PA LOGS SU MI DGOS PAR
Now a very interesting idea.
He says, "By the way,
you don't need to study step number four."
You don't need to study step number four.
Then you like, "What? I'm
studying it right now."
He says, "No, you don't need to study it."
Recognize that people
have been your mother.
Think about the kindness they showed you.
Think about paying back the kindness
and then automatically,
we can see a picture here,
You're on a auto pilot, right?
You don't have to steer the car.
Your mind will go directly
to seeing her as beautiful.
Once you decide that you
would like to push her,
your mom into enlightenment,
of course, you're going
to see her as beautiful.
So Pabongka Rinpoche says,
step number four is kind of automatic.
If you do the first three steps,
then the fourth step is going
to come up just automatically.
You don't have to think about it.
'DI LA DMIGS PA LOGS SU MI
DGOS PAR GONG GI MAR SHES
DRIN DRAN DRIN GZO GSUM
LA SNGON DU MYONG BA THON
MYONG BA THON means get good at them.
If you get good at the first three steps:
see them as your mom, think
about what they did for you,
want to pay them back;
RANG SHUGS KYIS 'BYUNG BA
RANG SHUGS KYIS means
means it's just going
to happen automatically.
SEMS CAN THAMS CAD KYI
RGYUD LA ZAG MED KYI BDE BA
LTA GA LA YOD DE ZAG BCAS
KYI BDE BA TZAM YANG MI 'DUG
But what's the current
state of all beings?
SEMS CAN THAMS CAD
What's going on with all
the people in the universe?
ZAG MED KYI BDE BA LTA GA LA
LTA GA LA YOD DE means forget it.
They don't have ultimate
happiness in their hearts.
Forget it.
They don't even have normal
happiness in their hearts.
They can't get even normal happiness.
We're supposed to be paying our mom back
by taking her to ultimate happiness.
But right now we can't even
give her regular happiness, even
for a few minutes difficult
to make another person happy.
DA LTA KHO RANG TSOS BDE BAR RLOM PA
DE YANG SDUG BSNGAL GYI
RANG BZHIN LAS MA 'DAS PAS
No, no, Geshe-la, my
mom is happy sometimes.
I'm also happy sometimes.
That's just suffering in another suit.
No, no, I have some
happy moments in my life.
It's just suffering with sugar on top.
It's just another kind of suffering.
Most of the things you think are happiness
are really just pain with
a little sugar on top.
DA NI SEMS CAN THAMS CAD
BDE BA THAMS CAD DANG
LDAN NA CI MA RUNG
You can talk about trying
to make all people,
give them ultimate happy,
give them all the happiness they can want.
CI MA RUNG
Yeah, that would be nice.
CI MA RUN
And by the way,
here we get into our kind
of Tibetan philosophy,
which is very close to
the Four Immeasurables.
The steps in the Four Immeasurables.
SEMS CAN THAMS CAD BDE BA THAMS CAD DANG
LDAN NA CI MA RUNG
LDAN PAR GYUR CIG, LDAN
PAR BDAG GIS BYA'O,
DE LTAR BYED NUS PAR BLA MA
LHAS BYIN GYIS BRLAB TU GSOL
This is a very, very famous formula.
May all the moms in my
world have happiness.
Wouldn't that be nice?
CI MA RUNG means wouldn't that be nice?
Wouldn't that be cool?
LDAN PAR GYUR CIG -- Yeah!
They should have happiness.
DE LTA BU DANG LDAN PA ZHIG BDAG GIS BYA'O
I'll do it. I'll take care of
it. I'll take responsibility.
So "wouldn't it be nice"
changes to "they should
have it", changes to
"I'll be the one who makes sure they get".
So three steps here: CI MA RUNG
Hey, how nice it would be
if all my moms were happy?
LDAN PAR GYUR CIG - Yeah, they
should. Let's make it happen.
I'll make it happen.
So those are the three steps.
We can see three steps
here in the picture.
Sometimes it takes me a
long time to find a picture.
Sometimes it just comes right away.
Yeah, three steps.
So tell me the three.
Number one. CI MA RUNG.
Wouldn't that be nice if
all my moms could be happy?
Then GYUR CIG
Yeah! That should happen.
Step number two.
Then step number three:
I'll make it happen.
I'll take responsibility.
By the way in the immeasurables,
there's a fourth step that
he doesn't mention here.
DE LTAR BYED NUS PAR BLA MA
LHAS BYIN GYIS BRLAB TU GSOL
What does that mean?
Yeah. Hey Lama. Hey Teacher.
Teacher, Lama and Angel, Lama-hla.
Please, help me do it.
He didn't have it here.
DE LTAR BYAMS PA BSGOMS PA'I PHAN YON NI
So if you have this kind
of attraction to people,
love for people -- BSGOMS PA NI --
what's going to happen to you,
if you reach a place in your life,
when you're looking at other people
and they just look beautiful
to you? What's the karma?
What kind of karma is that?
What happens to you if
you have this karma?
RIN PHRENG LAS means
RIN CHEN PHRENG BA LAS
It's ratna, not mala.
What's the other word for mala?
There's another Sanskrit
word for mala, for a garland.
[Student] (unclear)
ratna....
You look it up.
It has two names.
Some people say ratna.
And some people say, I forgot it.
,RDZI 'U TSOS SUM BRGYA'I KHA ZAS DAG,
,NYIN RE DUS GSUM SBYIN PAS KYANG,
,BYAMS PA YUD TZAM THANG GCIG GI,
,BSOD NAMS DAG LA CHAR MI PHOD,
There's a famous story
that you cook beautiful dishes for others,
especially for a group of monks or nuns.
You cook for 300 of them every day,
and three times you give them
breakfast, lunch, and dinner.
So the idea is like, I don't know,
you invite the Dalai Lama,
you invite some holy being to your house
and you feed them 300 homemade dishes
three times in one day.
But even compared to
feeding these high lamas,
high nuns, high monks,
BYAMS PA YUD TZAM means, if
you just have a passing moment
in your life, where you're like,
"Oh, these people are so beautiful,"
if you just have that thought
just go through your mind
one time like that,
"Oh, these people are so beautiful,"
it's more powerful than
serving thousands of meals
to very high lamas.
It's more good karma
than feeding all these
meals to high lamas.
BSOD NAMS DAG LA CHAR MI PHOD
CHAR MI PHOD means you
can't compare the karma.
CHAR MI PHOD means it doesn't make 1%.
The karma of serving, of cooking,
what do you call that, homemade meal
for a thousand high lamas
or just having a passing thought
"oh, these people around
me are so beautiful,"
I would like them to be happy.
That's better karma, more good karma.
You got that?
Come on, ratnamala.
I'm going to tell you later.
You can find it.
His book is not called Ratnamala,
it's called something else.
[Student] (unclear)
No, keep looking.
I'll look it up later.
Here's a verse. He's
going to quote a verse.
,LHA MI BYAMS PAR 'GYUR BA DANG,
this is what's going to happen
to you if you...
This is the power of the
karma, of sitting on a chair
and looking at other people and
feel like they're beautiful.
They're like my own kid and,
"I would like you to be happy.
You look so beautiful to me."
LHA MI BYAMS PAR 'GYUR
BA, the LHAs and the MIs
will be BYAMS PA to you.
What's that mean?
The powerful gods, worldly gods,
and also the tantric gods and humans,
they will like you.
When you meet people, they'll
be friendly to you and say,
"Hi, good morning."
I went this morning for a
blood test, regular checkup.
And the lady was so nice and she's just...
Boy, she has to sit there all day,
get up at four o'clock, five
o'clock, and she was so nice.
And that's just BYAMS PA.
People will be BYAMS PA to you.
DE DAG KYANG NI SRUNG BA DANG
They'll also take steps
to make sure you're okay.
They'll protect you,
like Jigme came and picked me up early
in the morning to go there.
YID BDE BA DANG
Then you'll always feel happy.
Deep down inside you'll feel happy.
This is from having those one
moments of vali, ratnavali.
YID BDE BA -- You'll feel happy
and BDE MANG means good
things will keep happening
to you all through the day.
By the way, what's this karma?
Just for a few seconds
you think about how beautiful
people are around you.
DUG DANG MTSON GYIS GNOD MED DANG
You can eat some bad
Mexican food in America
and it won't make you sick.
MTSON GYIS GNOD means people attack
you with a gun or a knife
and nothing will happen to you.
This is just from those moments
of thinking people are beautiful.
This is the karma.
There's eight of the karmas.
He's listing eight.
'BAD PA MED PAR DON 'THOB DANG
Without trying very hard,
all the stuff you want to
happen in your life will happen.
You will succeed in all
your projects and things
without much hard work.
TSANGS PA'I 'JIG RTEN SKYE 'GYUR TE
You'll be born into the
world of the pure one,
which sometimes means a kind
of a temporary god heaven,
and Brahma is the boss there.
But on a higher level, it
means a Buddha paradise.
GAL TE GROL BAR MA GYUR KYANG
Even if you don't get
enlightened right away,
just by those moments of
feeling love for people,
BYAMS CHOS YON TAN BRGYAD 'THOB BO
these eight wonderful things
will be happening to you.
ZHES GSUNGS PA LTAR, BYAMS CHOS
YON TAN BRGYAD 'THOB PA SOGS
PHAN YON SHIN TU CHE'O
Therefore, these eight
benefits of the karma,
of just seeing other people
as beautiful once in a while,
will come to you.
So that's a pretty easy way
to get a lot of beautiful
results is just to...
And normally, I mean,
I don't know about you.
If you're not in a good mood,
you're looking at people,
and driving your car,
and Geshe Michael's driving his car,
and he's like irritated at everybody.
We're talking about catch your mind
when it's being irritated at people
and then catch it and say, "Come on,
how beautiful are people?
people are beautiful."
You want to live by yourself in a closet?
It's not going to make you happy.
People are beautiful.
Go hang out with people.
Now, there's a very wonderful verse
by Arya Nagarjuna that I
would like to include here.
So I'm inserting a new
verse into the text.
This is one of my favorite
verses of all time.
If I'm not mistaken,
it's also the Ratnavali.
And I think, yeah.
Anyway, here it is.
I teach it to people in DCI a lot.
And I'd like you guys to,
I like to show it to you
because it's talking about
the power of that karma
of just thinking that the
people around you are beautiful.
Just for a few minutes
think of people around are beautiful.
So let's go through this verse.
You want to show this verse? Come on.
You have the verse on Nagarjuna?
Okay here we go.
I didn't put the pronunciation.
I didn't put the technical pronunciation
but I'll do it with you here.
Please say. You guys, ready?
danad
bhogah
sukham
shilat
kshantyah
kantih
shramad
dyutih
dhyarach
chantir
mater
muktih
kirpa
sarvartha
sadhani
Okay, good. Let's go through it.
These are the correlations,
karmic correlations
as presented by Nagarjuna,
extremely beautiful,
extremely complete in a single verse.
People tell me, "I want
to learn some Tibetan,
I want to learn some Sanskrit."
Then learn this verse.
This is a great verse to learn.
It's very powerful to
have verses in your mind.
It's like having Nagarjuna
talk to you all day long.
It's very beautiful.
So memorize it. Memorize it.
These are the karmic correlations
according to Arya Nagarjuna.
Danad bhogah
Danad... Dana means what, you guys?
Giving.
And then what's the long "a-t" in Sanskrit
at the end of a word?
Long "a-t"? Yeah, from.
From doing danad you will get this.
So he keeps repeating
this AT, which for an A,
a noun ending in A, means from.
Danad means from.
And the T changes to D
before a B, that's all. BH.
So danad.
What do you get from
giving things to people?
Bhogah. Bhogah means?
[Student] Enjoyment?
Yeah, lots of stuff.
Like sambhogakaya, right?
You get money. You're
going to get prosperous.
Your life is going to be full of
money, houses, cars, things,
beautiful things, nice
things, good things to have.
You can have more money
to help ALL, for example.
Just call the "Club de oro".
But you get that money
to give to good charities
by dana.
Now because of poetry,
he has to say the next one backwards.
Shilat from shila.
Yeah, ethical lifestyle.
Literally shila means...
Do you know? Means what?
Cool and refreshing. Shila.
So shilat... From being
nice to other people
you get sukha.
You just feel happy all the time.
So by the way, by now
you can see that he's going
through the six perfections.
What's the next one that we expect?
Yeah. Don't get upset.
Kshantyah means patience.
Kshanti means patience.
And this KSH in Sanskrit
often changes to QUI in English.
So quiet,
like quiet from peacefulness.
You get kantih.
Kantih means golden.
De oro... d'oro?
That's kantih.
It means golden complexion,
which means beauty,
either handsome or beautiful.
So either Pachi or Pau, you
can get from being patient,
in your past life.
Next life, we don't know yet.
So that means if you don't
get angry with people,
then your face will become
more and more beautiful.
He says golden.
Shramad dyutih.
Sharamad means like shramanera.
It means hard work.
And it also has an implication of fun.
If you have fun,
BRTZON GANG DGE LA SPRO BA'O
Shantideva defines the fourth perfection
as having fun, when you're
doing good stuff for people.
So just having fun, doing good things,
not bad things.
That's called the shrama.
And shramad dyutih,
dyutih is a very interesting word.
It's the modern Hindi
word for electricity.
Yeah, and it means you will
have an electric personality.
And it means you will become a leader.
People will be attracted to you.
You will have a powerful,
attractive personality.
What do you call that? You will be...
[Student] Charismatic?
[GMR] Charismatic, exactly.
That's called dyutih.
You will have an electric presence.
It's also the word for
lightning in ancient Sanskrit.
Dyutih
Dhyanach means... it's from dhyana,
from meditation.
Shanti
SHA changes to CHA after C.
So this chantir is shanti,
which means peaceful.
You will always be peaceful.
So he's going through the six perfections
and he's doing the karmic correlations
in a single beautiful verse.
And it's very good to memorize.
If you want to know some Sanskrit,
if you want to impress other
people at cocktail parties
in Lake Chapala,
around there and in those restaurants,
then learn one verse of Sanskrit.
Shanti. Mater means mati. Yeah, the mind,
meaning
you understand the two
husbands in the kitchen.
That's called mati.
And the ablative is mater,
from mates,
from understanding -- muktih,
you get free.
Yeah. You get freedom.
Freedom comes from
understanding your husband
in the kitchen when he yells at you.
Now, Geshe-la, why did you
put this verse in here?
We aren't talking about it.
I mean, that's very sweet, but
we aren't talking about that.
Yeah, but we're talking
about the next one,
which is kirpa sarvartha sadhani.
Kirpa means love.
Sarva means all.
Sarva atha means like Siddhartha, goals.
Sadhani -- you will reach...
This SADH means to reach.
You will reach all your goals.
What's he saying is that, and
that's very extraordinary.
And I think a lot of my
Christian friends would agree.
He says, Yeah, you can
practice those six perfections.
Those are important.
Each one has a powerful karmic result,
and, of course, you should practice them.
But actually, if you have five minutes
of true love for somebody else,
it achieves all those goals
together. All six goals.
Sarvartha -- you get all six
goals together by having 5
or 10 minutes of real
love for somebody else,
beautiful love, beauty love, right?
Cool? So don't forget that one.
A passing moment where
you think all the people
around you are super beautiful
is equal to the karma of
those six perfections?
Wow.
Or feeding a million monks.
All right.
Next part of the text.
BYAMS PA BSGOM PA 'DI'I DMIGS
YUL DU CI TZAM KHYAB PAS
Now when you feel people are beautiful,
the bigger you can make that feeling,
the more you can multiply the karma.
The more people you
feel beautiful love for,
the more that love is powerful.
KHYAB PAS
DE TZAM LA DBANG BA'I 'KHOR BSGYUR DANG
TSANGS PAR SKYE BAR 'GYUR
If you can kind of stretch
it out to more people,
the karma is that you will
become 'KHOR LO SGYUR BA,
chakravartin, yeah.
Wheel emperor, yeah. What's the wheel?
A spaceship.
It means King of the World.
It's means President of the Whole World.
So it's interesting.
If you have these occasional feelings
that people around you are
beautiful and you love them,
that's a very powerful good karma.
If you can just push it a little further
towards more people, then it's
going to suddenly multiply
and you will be King of the World.
That's not much.
Okay, 10 more people.
- Hey, you want to be
king of the world? - Yeah.
- Do you feel beautiful love for people?
- Like a couple.
- Can you just stretch
it to 10 more people?
You can be King of the World if you do.
- Okay. I'll do that.
DE TZAM LA DBANG BA'I 'KHOR BSGYUR DANG
TSANGS PAR SKYE BAR 'GYUR
TSANGS PA means this very powerful
worldly god, Brahma,
who rules over entire realms of planets,
a billion worlds.
'DI LA TSANGS PA'I GNAS ZHES
BYA BA'ANG DE'I PHYIR YIN LA
That's why the verse above said
you can go to the place of Brahma
if you have this beautiful love.
NAM MKHA'I MTHA' KHYAB
KYI SEMS CAN THAMS CAD LA
DMIGS PAS NI
But if you can stretch that
beautiful love to all beings
equal in extent to the universe itself,
TSANGS PA CHEN PO MI GNAS PA'I MYANG 'DAS
we call it the great brahma,
maha brahma, meaning buddhahood.
You can reach buddhahood.
Just try to stretch your
beautiful love a little wider.
All right.
That brings us to...
How many we've got?
MAR SHES, DRIN DRAN, DRIN GZO,
YI 'ONG BYAMS PA, SNYING RJE
Is it? Are we on five?
MAR SHES, DRIN DRAN, DRIN GZO,
YI 'ONG BYAMS PA, SNYING RJE
Yeah, we're on number five.
SNYING RJE CHEN PO -- great compassion,
maha karuna, here we go.
LNGA PA SNYING RJE CHEN PO NI
Let's go onto number five,
step number five of the
seven cause and effect
for getting bodhisattva vision.
SNYING RJE CHEN PO NI What is it?
What is great compassion?
SANGS RGYAS KYI THUN MONG
MIN PA'I NYE RGYU GRUNG PO
GRUNG PO means this is the real sharp
and effective tool
that can help you reach
enlightenment itself.
So now we're talking about compassion.
Generally, the difference
between compassion
and... what you say...
Well, you can say BYAMS PA means that
you love people.
You feel maitri, compassion,
and then SNYING RJE means you want
to help them escape their pain.
So BYAMS PA is you want
them to have something nice,
and SNYING RJE means you
want them to escape pain.
And we're going to get to it
later, but there's a big debate
about, some people say
BYAMS PA comes first.
You know, first you have to love someone,
like your own child
and then you can want
to take their pain away.
And some people say, no, no, no.
If a child falls down off of a
bicycle and hurts themselves,
you don't give them candy.
You fix the pain first, and
then you give them love.
So compassion and love.
GRUNG PO ZHIG YIN LA,
RJE RIN PO CHES KYANG
RJE RIN PO CHES -- Je Tsongkapa said,
LAM RIM CHEN PO'I NANG BYANG
CHUB SEMS SBYONG GI RIM PA'I
SA BCAD MDZAD PA NA
When Tsongkapa outlines the steps
for getting to bodhichitta
or the bodhisattva's vision,
he said in his LAM RIM CHEN MO,
in his great Lam Rim,
SNYING RJE CHEN PO THEG CHEN
GYI LAM GYI RTZA BAR BSTAN
He said the whole seven
steps turn on compassion.
All seven steps turn on compassion.
Compassion is the center
of the airplane prop.
And everything turns on compassion.
Je Tsongkapa describes that way.
Yes, there are seven steps,
but number five is the one
that everything turns around.
He thought it was the most important one.
RGYU 'BRAS GZHAN RNAMS DE'I
RGYU 'BRAS SU 'GRO TSUL
When you describe the
others as cause and effect,
you're really not talking
about cause and effect of bodhichitta.
You're talking about
compassion as cause and effect.
The relationship of all
the other five steps
is that they are either
causes of compassion
or results of compassion.
And that's why we call this thing
the five cause and effect steps.
It's not that bodhichitta is the effect.
It's that everything is
defined relative to compassion.
He thought it was that important.
'GRO TSUL ZHES DMIGS KYIS BSAL TE
DMIGS KYIS BSAL TE means he
gave a unique explanation.
DMIGS BSAL means special or unique.
It's a very important
word in the monastery
because DMIGS BSAL means
you have a formal exception
from the abbot.
You don't have to wash dishes.
You don't have to do farming.
I got a DMIGS BSAL for farming
because I was the accountant.
So you know, they made
me farm for one day.
This is standing on an ox,
standing on the back of an ox.
And I died after the
first day and they said,
"You stick to accounting,
you have a DMIGS BSAL.
You don't have to go
out to do the farming."
So that's called DMIGS BSAL.
Here, compassion is a DMIGS BSAL.
Compassion is a special case.
Everything turns around compassion,
according to Tsonkgapa.
I like this picture of kids
jumping into the water.
We were discussing what
country it should be.
We don't know yet.
But it seems to me from compassion
you can jump off into
BDAG GZHAN MNYAM BRJE.
What is BDAG GZHAN MNYAM
BRJE? Equal and exchange.
Equal and exchange.
Equal means every living being
has a right to happiness,
equal right.
Exchange means, put
yourself in other's shoes
and watch you and see how
hard you are on people.
It's funny.
It doesn't mean, I'm
going to pretend I'm Pau,
and I'm going to be nice or something.
It doesn't mean that. It
means I'm going to be Pau
and look at Geshe Michael,
and see how much trouble
is Geshe Michael for Pau.
So you can do equal.
I'm equal to you. We have
equal right to happiness.
Why should Geshe-la send somebody else out
to get a croissant?
Why can't other people send Geshe-la out
That would be equal, right.
And then, how does it
feel when Geshe-la says,
"You go get me a croissant",
but Geshe-la doesn't say,
"I'll go get you a croissant?"
It feels unfair. It feels unequal, right?
So this is the two steps of MNYAM BRJE.
If you can empathize
with other people's pain,
then you can exchange
yourself with others.
If you can be aware
that someone else feels bad
about croissant running,
if you reach that kind of
awareness or sensitivity
to other people's feelings,
then you can exchange,
then you can exchange.
So this is a good place to jump off.
If you want to do the other great method
of getting to bodhichitta,
which is two steps:
see that you're equal to others
and then put yourself in
their eyes and look at you.
That's the second classical
way to get bodhichitta.
And this is a good place to
jump off from the five steps
to jump to the two steps of Shantideva.
This is a good place to jump.
If you feel like there's a
special meditation practice,
called, what is that called?
I forgot.
[Student] Exchange yourself and others?
[GMR] No, this is like... you go up
through the eight form realm levels
and then you go up to
the eight, the four...
Sorry, four and four.
It's called %SPEL SGOM.
%SPEL SGOM means you don't go
one, two, three, four,
five, six, seven, eight.
You go one, three, five, seven, six, four
and you jump around.
So if you feel like it,
this is Geshe Michael giving
you an extra assignment.
It's not in the text.
If you want to get fancy
and you want to challenge yourself,
try to jump between the two methods
of getting to bodhichitta.
The first is the five steps
that we've been studying.
And the second is BDAG GZHAN MNYAM BRJE.
Equal, equal, become aware
that you are equal to others
and then try to see how they see you.
Which is called exchanging
self and others.
But it's not what you think.
It's not like put yourself in other shoes.
It doesn't mean that.
It means put yourself in Christina's body
and look at Geshe Michael
and see how it feels to be Christina.
How is Geshe Michael treating Christina?
See how it feels to Christina
to look at Geshe Michael
and see how he treats her.
So you can get a bodhichitta either way.
What I'm saying is, Tsongkapa said,
the five steps for getting
to bodhichitta, they turn
around step number five...
Sorry, the seven steps, turn
around step number five.
And I'm saying another cool
thing is, if you want to,
you can jump from step
five to Shantideva's way
of getting bodhichitta.
Right now we studying Atisha's way
of getting bodhichitta, right?
All right, here we go.
MDO LAS KYANG, 'KHOR
BSGYUR GYI 'KHOR LO DANG,
MI'I SROG GI DBANG PO LTAR
THEG CHEN GYI LAM 'BRAS BU DANG
BCAS PA THAMS CAD KYANG
'DI LA RAG LAS PAR GSUNGS SHING,
If you are a wheel emperor or a...
what do you call a flying saucer king?
You need your flying saucer.
If you're a bodhisattva,
you need your compassion.
What he says here is
'KHOR BSGYUR GYI 'KHOR LO
If you're going to be a spaceship king
you better get a spaceship.
If you're going to be a bodhisattva,
you better get some compassion.
Or if you want to be a living human being,
and not a stone or a tree,
you better have some life,
human life inside your body.
So what he's saying is, in
the way that life animates
the human body, compassion
animates the human soul.
All right, 'DI LA RAG LAS PAR GSUNGS SHING
Cool, we finished this class
and then we're going to go on to...
We're going to take a trip to Tsongkapa's
greatest book on emptiness
because there's something there
that's going to help us
with our bodhichitta.
See you in the next class. Yay!